Guide to the Hopkins Transportation Collection, 1868-1936
Department of Special Collections
Hopkins Transportation Collection,
1868-1936
Special Collections M164
6 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Gift of the Public Utilities Commission, through James Gibson, 1962-1964.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This collection consists largely of working papers for applications to, hearings before, etc., the California Railroad Commission (forerunner of the Public Utilities Commission) or the Interstate Commerce Commission, 1912-1915, 1922-1923, 1927-1930, 1932-1933, and 1936. Also included are reports, histories, statistics, briefs, maps, diagrams, etc. giving background material on a number of the smaller California railroads (lumber, street, interurban and/or electric). There is very little correspondence in the collection.
CONTAINER LIST
- Bakersfield & Kern Electric Railway. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Historical Study of Accounts, 1900-1915 of above and Valuation 1915.
  - Notes on Franchises, land, equipment, etc., Calif. RR Comm.
  - Valuation 1922.
- Cement, Tolenas & Tidewater Railroad Co. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Report of Value 1915,notes, valuations
- Death Valley Railroad (Box 1, Folder 2a)
  - History and valuation 1915.
- Carson & Colorado Railroad (Box 1, Folder 2b)
  - Corresp. re: "The Man, Mink"
  - Lookover the way-bills
  - Photocopy of 1890 Guide (C connection with Va. & Truckee).
  - Receipts - 1882
  - Minke - 1889
- Fresno Traction Co. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Historical valuation of street rail-way showing progress & cost of construction, prices track, roadway, work papers 1922.
- Glendale & Montrose Railroad Co. (electric). (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1915valuations
- Great Northern & Western Pacific Railroads. (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Material re: proposed connection & expansion in 1929 & 1930.
  - Letters, circular, brochure, address, I.C.C. application, A.G. Mott - direct examination, statistics & reports for I.C.C., talk by John Edward Cooper, (typescript).
- Memphis and Vicksburg RR (Box 1, Folder 6b)
- Minarets and Western Railway Co. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1923application to build, map showing location in conjunction with other local railways.
- Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1927Valuation of Electric, Street & Interurban Railroads
  - 1928Sales contract - sale of Indian Valley RR Co. by Engels Copper Mining Co. to Western Pacific RR Corp.
- Nevada and California Railway Co. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Valuations 1912,maps, construction chart, rates, cost data, comments and field book, (Became part of Central Pacific at this time.)
- Northern Electric Railway. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Diagrams, charts, electrical statistics, grading specifications, schedule, financial statistics.
- Northwestern Pacific Railroad Co. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Application for bond issue 19l4,3 valuations 1912 and 1913,and general statistics 1933.
- Ocean Shore Railway Co. (Box 1-2, Folder 12-13)
  - Inventories & Appraisals 1912,Abstracts, Physical Valuation, Company's appraisal, List depots' grounds, legal opinion, draft of report, mortgage, field notes, equipment reports, valuations 1913.
- Pacific Electric Railway Co. (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - California Railroad Commn. re: rates, equipment, etc., on hauling rock, sand & gravel, statistics, maps; Pasadena rates - street car-motor coach, maps, statistics, inventories, memos, reports
- Petaluma & Santa Rosa Electrix Railroad Co. (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - Profiles 1912,field books, Physical Valuation 1914,Appraisal 1913.
- Sacramento Street Railway (owned by P.G. & E.) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Maps, history of track construction, printed brochures, 1927Capital Business, rates, valuation 1927(P.E. Dufour).
  - Sacramento Valley RR (pamphlet)
- San Diego & Arizona Railway (Box 2-3, Folder 19-20)
  - Valuations and reports 1912-14,field books notes, work papers, diagrams, memos. See also San Diego & South Eastern Ry.
- San Diego & South Eastern Railway Co. (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
  - Valuations, reports, memos, notes, maps, field books, history includes that of predecessors. See also San Diego & Arizona Ry.
- San Diego Electric Railway Co. (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
  - 1914Petition & exhibits, maps, plans, statistics, valuations, reports, statements of construction, records, notes, drafts, appraisals, diagrams.
- San Francisco Napa & Calistoga Railroad. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Statistics, reports, agreements on electrical accounts, valuations, field book.
- South San Francisco Belt Railway. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Valuations, reports.
- Southern Pacific Co. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - 1887"Passes are Prohibited"
  - 1930Index Common Standard Drawings
  - 1929Agreement with Red River Lumber Co., 1928 Annual Report.
- Stockton Terminal & Eastern Railroad Co. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Valuations, statistics notes.
- Tidewater Southern Railway Co. (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Register of deeds, statistics valuations, brochure, reports, extracts.
- Transportation Case 3154 (1932) (Box 4, Folder 30-33)
  - Investigation by C.R.C. on its own motion of the transportation systems of the state in 1932. Work papers, memos, statistics, tables, charts, statements, proposals, diagrams, questionnaire, printed material, exhibits, digest of transcripts.
- Union Pacific System. (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Common Standard Drawings.
- Photographs
  - Great Northern - Western Pacific n.d. (Box 5, Folder 35-36)
    Aerial photos of S.P. lines, timber lands, barren lands, other RRs, grazing lands, etc. in northeastern & central eastern California. Reconnaissance maps of above.
  - Southern Pacific Company, Pacific Lines, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    Track -Klamath Falls to Alturas, Shows various points on route, roadside equipment.
  - Southern Pacific Company, Pacific Lines, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    Same as above, but much more complete, more photos, incl. Hackamore Station, Lakeview station, Altural station, etc. Also includes route pictures of N.C. & 0. & Fernley Lassen Branch, Long Bell Lumber Co., Railroad, McCloud River Lumber Co. RR, Lassen Lumber & Box Co. Logging RR, Fruit Growers Supply Co. Logging RR, and some highways.
  - Southern Pacific Co. Pacific Lines 1929 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    Aerial photos with red inked lines & location names, South Keddie to Klamath Falls,
  - Traffic Congestion and Hazards 1936, 2 v. (Box 5, Folder 40-41)
    Dangerous situations and near accidents caused by slow trucks, blockage of highway by passing vehicles, passing on wrong side or in front of oncoming traffic, weaving, passing on hills and blind curves, etc.
  - Survey of Railroad Crossings on State Highways in California 1922. (Box 5, Folder 42)
    Loose photos, numbers on verso refer to corresponding location numbers on enclosed map, some unidentified.
- Pacific Electric Roll Map. Shows various lines & routes of system in Los Angeles & environs. (Tube 6)
- 1916Calif. Oil Fields and Oil Pipe Lines (Tube 6)
- Virginia and Truckee Railroad Company., Xerox copies of originals in the Yerington Collection, Department of Special Collections, University of Nevada Library. (Folder 43)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1868-1875.
  - List of stockholders/dividends.